Human interaction.
Go ahead and start when you're ready.
Yeah,
I don't have much to show on my screen.
I'm doing this from the phone
and the site of mine. Yes.
You know, it's playing
tricks on the phone at this point.
I'm gonna fix this at some point, but now
I will just send the link in the comment.
So hello everybody.
My name is Kerala Zuni.
I want to speak a little bit
about human digital interaction,
which is a broadly defined way
to describe a panel session
that I used to host.
I hosted a panel session
about five years ago,
from early 2021
to late 2022, and
that panel was
it was called Practical Knowledge
in Digital Arts.
It was a serious of sessions, a panel
consisting of a series of sessions, and
it involved people from
various from different
fields of digital arts,
like from game studies to to electronic
literature scholars and artists
or the other way around.
So I will just give you the the link here.
I slink to to site of mine.
It's right on top of it.
I mean, and the head says it all about the
I mean, like,
the contributors are all quieted there
in the head of it,
and they very optical is on top
because it is an article,
because the very idea of the panel was
that we would make an article out of it.
And the article is about how we see
digital art,
digital literary art, mostly
as something that is primarily, primarily
fulfilled by the readers.
So the point was that
the ball is on the side
of the reader, right?
Because it doesn't matter how it's written
anymore, as much as how it is read.
And when I was working with the like
on the article,
when I was doing an article
out of our panel sessions,
I got feedback from the contributors.
And a lot of this feedback was that.
Now with the developments of AI,
it all looks very different
because when we were discussing
practical knowledge
in digital arts, like the
things that we practically do
with with digital texts,
we were discussing something that related
to interactivity, to pure interactivity.
And it was absolutely
like evidence that
a reader is is an active agent in this.
Right.
And this process, by these days,
we kind of revisit
or revisit this topic,
and the idea is to revisit
this kind of concept
of practical knowledge
that kind of embodies a reader in
an electronic literature piece.
The question is what we have
that keeps the human agency intact in it,
because over the recent years,
first of all, the AI,
the first thing that AI did
was, of course,
it is that it changed the authorship.
So definitely you don't have
to be human to write a text.
But another thing is that you
don't have to be a human to read a text.
And this has.
Interesting practical aspect in it.
I want to tell you a little bit
about my experience
as as a Russian citizen as well,
because I am a Russian Israeli
citizen and I get news from Russia,
and I know how
AI is used to read texts there
to in order to, you know,
make cases for courts.
This is what I heard.
Like there was a case recently
when somebody was
charged, like criminally charged
for something that was most probably
the community came up with this
conclusion was probably found by AI.
So the texts of the poets that are in
Russia are moving toward
AI due to certain protocols and words.
This is how it looks like.
So the reader becomes
also inhuman.
On the other side,
we also have an inhuman agent.
So in and the problem arrives, I think,
when we always have something else
on the other side.
Right.
So we don't have this,
we cannot anymore assume
that we communicate with each other,
which is normal, which is kind of cliche
to say, but what do we do with this?
So the question is
how do we keep human agency, right.
So when we were doing this panel,
when we were doing those panel sessions,
the assumption was that there will always
be a human on the other side.
And the case was still
that we assume
that the writer is also human,
though using,
well, automated tools, of course.
Right.
But still human being.
So now we have
this kind of
situation when we don't always know
if this is human text or not,
and we never know
if our text is going to be read
by human, which is also
quite, quite common knowledge.
But the question is, how do we keep human?
And it's always a question
at this point of.
How we process the texts.
And this is something
that we also discussed in that article.
And revisiting that article
that I wrote out of
the panel discussions,
is that like when revisiting it,
I'm thinking about how the structure
of digital
text of an AI text is either
recreated by a reader or not recreated.
So in other words,
the question is to what extent readership
is the reverse engineering of writing?
And this is something
that I've been interested
for years, though now it seems to be one.
Well, one of the things, one of the core
agendas in the
country where I come from,
right, in Russia, in terms of how
texts are being processed
in legal system,
for instance, as well, right.
How they are read, how they are traced
and what they are.
Also referred to an article by
is a recent one is called is digital
art a visual art and.
In this in this article
he speaks about visuality
and his core point.
I want to quote here he compares
a visual artifact
and Elektronik visual artifact.
He says the introduction of visual arts,
contemplative or instrumental.
The image is the thing that communicates
in such a much excuse me, of digital art
that elsewhere, through the exchange,
the argument or the method.
So basically what he says
is that it can look like a visual art,
but it not necessarily is represented.
You know, it doesn't represent represents
necessarily by a random visual per se.
So we could refer to Marshall
McLuhan here, maybe.
Who said that?
Well, is TV a visual thing?
No, he said it's a wave, right?
It is something else.
So it can look like a visual thing,
but it can as well be something else.
So the question is, how do we read
those texts
that are made by by AI, right?
I mean, this is
something that has been discussed,
like everybody's talking about AI,
like literally, but
the yeah, I am, I am actually up.
My point is and my,
my point was our point of discussion,
our agenda was when we were doing
those panel discussions was.
A reader's role is different
in interactive digital literature.
And now
we are dealing with
texts that can look normal
and be normal.
And I mean like an informal way and
be an end.
Pretend to be
genuine testimony, for instance.
But it's even more distant from.
A normal art,
from a from a traditional art.
Then our hypertext works
because structurally is very different.
And the human, the human
agency remains on the other side,
the human remains, the reader,
the reader remains human.
And it's becoming even more urgent,
even more pressing
to maintain this human agency
because it's substituted both on the
a level
of writing
and on the level of reading itself.
Which doesn't mean that AI and digital art
is not
kind of something good for humanity,
of course.
But the thing is
that when there is this tension
between human and digital,
there is human element in it, right?
So yes, I do believe that
when revisiting this article,
which you can read, all of you,
I gave you the link in this article.
I think that, yeah, we will
write about this when we said that.
It's about the other side, it's about the
reader and it's about the human reader.
Because as long as the reader
remains human,
we are dealing with human art,
whatever it is.
Right?
Like however it was made.
So yeah, I don't know what else to say.
Is there are any questions? Yeah.
I mean, my
my purpose was just to, to, to give you
knowledge of this article that we did
with the great dear contributors
and to kind of show change context
that we are in
now with the recent developments of AI.
So if there are any questions.
We'll we'll hold off on questions
to the end possible
so we can get all the presenters together.
Sure. Yeah. Fair enough. Fair enough.